בוקר טוב, Boker tov, חנוכה שמח. Chanukah Sameach. We pick up, God
willing today we end the sixth פרק. perek. We pick up at
the bottom of ס"ו עמוד ב', Samech Vav Amud Bet, today's דף
daf is ס"ז, Samech Zayin, 67. Anyway, we pick up where the
גמרא Gemara says ואמר אביי. v'amar Abaye. It is ten lines from
the bottom, the line starts with the word מאי תיקו. mai teiku.
We're in the middle of various things that אביי Abaye is reporting
from his nurse-maid who he calls his mother. He was brought up
as an orphan. That were done for different incantations or whatever they
were done for healing purposes. So because that was the context in
which the גמרא Gemara understood why these young boys were wearing knots,
various knotted things. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר אביי, v'amar Abaye,
אביי Abaye says, אמרה לי אם, Amra li em, my mother said
to
me, לאשתא בת יומא, l'eshta bas yoma, that's one day old, לישקל
זוזא חיורא, lisque zuza chivera, take a white coin, וליזיל למילחא, v'leizil
l'milcha, go to the salt mines or, you know, not salt mines
but where they would actually dry out, they, sea water, it would
evaporate and create salt. They still do that. I know, I see
it near the Dead Sea. ולישקל מתקליה מילחא, v'lisque maskalei milcha, make,
take the equal weight of this coin in salt, וליצרי בחללא דבי
צוארא, v'litzrei b'chalala d'bei tzavra, and put it in the hollow of
your neck. I think this means right here, you know the place
where it meets like the breastplate, there's this little hollow here. Anyway,
put it in the hollow of your neck
בנירא ברקא b'nira barka with a string of hair, and there it'll
heal you. ואי לא, v'ee lo, and if you can't do that,
ליתיב בפרשת דרכים, leisev b'parashas drachim, sit by the crossroads like Tamar
went to
פרשת עיניים. parashas einayim. Anyway, so back explains it, וכי חזי שומשומנא
גמלא, v'chi chazi shumshumana gamla, and when you see an
ant, a big ant, דדרי מידי, d'dari midi, that's carrying something on
its
back, לישקליה, lisaklei, take the ant, ולישדיה בגובתא דנחשא, v'lishdi b'guvta d'nechasha,
put it in a tube of copper, וליסתמייה באברא, v'listamye b'avra, and
seal it with lead, וליחתמיה בשיתין גושפנקי, v'lichtamye b'shishin gushpanki, and seal
it with
sixty seals. רש"י Rashi says sixty is an exaggeration. וליברזליה, v'lebarzlei, and
go ahead and shake it, ולידריה, v'lidrei, and carry it,
this tube that has the ant in it, ולימא ליה, v'leime lei,
and say to the ant, טונך עלי, tunach alai, your burden should
be on
me, וטונאי
עלך, v'tunai alach, and what my burden should be on you and
you should take my fever. Okay, good thing it's not proportional because
ants carry what, 600 times their weight or something? Anyway, fine. אמר
רב אחא בריה דרב הונא לרב אשי, Amar Rav Acha brei d'Rav
Huna l'Rav Ashi, רב אחא Rav Acha the son of רב הונא
Rav Huna said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ודילמא איניש אשכחיה ואיפסק
ביה, v'dilma inish aschach v'ifsak bei, one minute, maybe this same ant
was used by somebody else and he used it to stop his
fever. So now the ant has this other guy's fever. So if
you're exchanging it, it doesn't do you any good. He's carrying the
other guy's burden, yeah, but whatever. אלא לימא ליה, ella leime lei,
so rather say, טונאי וטונך עלך, tunai v'tunach alach, my burden and
your burden is on you. All right, now what I find is
interesting is that they think that they can ask like rational questions
about the incantation,
right, and change the incantations. So they actually think, meaning, you know,
there's something here that they think there's some logic, something is really
manipulating something so you can like raise issues and redefine it. Anyway,
we'll see that again, but I find that fascinating. ואי לא, v'ee
lo, and if somehow you can't do that, you can't find an
ant or a copper tube, לישקול כוזא חדתא, lisque kuza chadta, go
take a new little flask, וליזיל לנהרא, v'leizel l'nahara, go to the
river, ולימא ליה, v'leime lei, and say to the river, נהרא נהרא,
Nahara Nahara, river, river, אוזפן כוזא דמיא, oizfen kuza d'maya, lend me
a flask of water, לאורחא דאיקלע לי, l'orcha d'ikla li, for a
guest that visited me, meaning the fever is the guest. And presumably
you fill it up with water, the flask. ליהדריה שבע זימני ארישיה,
l'hadr'ei shev zimnei a'reisha, and spin it seven times around your head,
ולישדיה לאחוריה, v'lishdi l'acharei, and throw behind your
back, ולימא ליה, v'leime lei, and then say, נהרא נהרא, Nahara Nahara,
river, river, שקול מיא דיהבת לי, shkol maya d'yavta li, take back
the water you've given me, דאורחא דאיקלע לי, d'orcha d'ikla li, the
guest that visited me, ביומא אתא ביומא אזל, b'yoma asa b'yoma azal,
this day has arrived and in this day shall leave. And somehow
that'll cause the fever to depart. Okay. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav
Huna, so now that was for a one-day fever. Said רב הונא,
Rav Huna, לאשתא תילתא, l'eshta silsa, for a three-day fever, or רש"י
Rashi might say that it has come back three times. Anyway, a
three-day fever, לייתי שבע סילויא, leisei sheva siluyei, take seven thorns, משבע
דיקלי, misheva diklei, from seven palms. רש"י Rashi is at the top
of ס"ז עמוד א'. Samech Zayin Amud Alef. ושבע ציבי משבע כשרי,
v'sheva tzivei misheva kishrei, and seven splinters from seven beams, ושבע סיכי
משבע גישרי, v'sheva sichei misheva gishrei, and seven pegs from seven
bridges, ושבע קיטמי משבע תנורי, v'sheva kitmi misheva tanuri, and seven... servings
of ashes or whatever from seven ovens, ושבעה עפרי משבעה סנרי v'shiva
afrei m'shiva sanrei and seven measures of dust from seven sockets, door
sockets, ושבעה קופי משבעה ארבי v'shiva kufi m'shiva arvi and seven scrapings
of tar from seven boats, ושבעה בוני כמוני v'shiva bunei kamuni and
seven seeds of cumin, ושבעה ביני מדיקנא
דכלבא סבא v'shiva binei mi'dikna d'kalba sava and seven hairs from the
beard of an old dog, וליציירהו בחללא דבית צוארא v'litzayrehu b'chalala d'veit
tzavara and bind it in the hollow of your
neck
בנירא ברקא b'nira barka with a string of hair. Okay,
that'll take care of the three-day-old one. I got to tell you,
maybe this is a silly question, but I'm reading this and I'm
wondering, like, where is he getting the seven pegs from the seven
bridges? Like, is he stealing them? Who, I mean, you know, I'm
serious. Does he own them?
To steal
something
that could be a medical treatment?
If enough people take seven pegs from the seven bridges, eventually they're
going to fall down.
Maybe they had stores of them.
Oh, that's interesting. Oh, that's an interesting thought. Maybe after they made
the bridge, they removed the pegs and put in other pegs? Right.
Somebody who has a healing...
oh, that's an interesting thought. Okay, could be. המשיכו מה. hamshikhuma.
All right, so that's for that.
אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: לאשתא צמירתא l'eshta tzmirtah for a
real intense fever,
רש"י Rashi says it's, yeah, רש"י Rashi says that it burns the
whole body, the whole body feels fire. לשקול סכינא דכולא פרזלא, Lishkol
sakina d'khula parzla, take a knife that is made totally out of
iron, וליזל להיכא דאיכא ורדינא, v'lezal l'heika d'ika vardina, go to where
there is some type of a bush. I think שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says
it's a mulberry bush, I don't know. What does it say? Thorn
bush? I don't know. ורד Vered is a rose, but anyway, some
type of a bush. וליקטור ביה נירא ברקא, v'liktor bei nira barka,
and tie on it again a string of hair. This string of
hair repeats itself a lot. יומא קמא, Yoma kama, the first day,
ליחרוק ביה פורתא, likhrok bei porta, make a little carving into this
bush, ולימא, v'leima, and say to it, וירא מלאך ה' אליו, Vayera
malach Hashem elav, and the
angel of God appeared to Moshe. Okay,
so how is this relevant? Because the end of it says, מדוע
לא יבער הסנה, Madua lo yivar hasneh, why will the bush not
be consumed by the fire, the heat, the fever? So somehow that
the fever should not consume you.
ולמחר, U'l'machar, the next day, ליחרוק ביה פורתא, likhrok bei porta, carve
a little bit into the bush, ולימא, v'leima, and say, ויאמר משה
אסורה נא ואראה, Vayomer Moshe asura na v'ereh, let me go and
see, מדוע לא יבער
הסנה. madua lo yivar hasneh. And the third day,
ולמחר, u'l'machar, the day after, ליחרוק ביה פורתא, likhrok bei porta, carve
a little bit, ולימא, v'leima, וירא ה' כי סר לראות, Vayar Hashem
ki sar lir'ot, God saw that he had turned. So the idea
of סר sar turned to be removed, that the fever should be
removed. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav
Aha brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi, ולימא, v'leima, how about I got another
פסוק pasuk will work here. ולימא ויאמר אל תקרב הלום, v'leima vayomer
al tikrav halom, do not draw nigh, so the fever, the illness
should not draw nigh onto you. So that's a good פסוק. pasuk.
אלא, Ella, so, ליומא
קמא לימא וירא מלאך ה' אליו ויאמר משה אסורה נא ואראה מדוע
לא יבער הסנה. l'yoma kama leima Vayera malach Hashem elav Vayomer Moshe
asura na v'ereh madua lo yivar hasneh. So do the whole
thing, right, because combine the first two days into one into the
first day, because the basic point of that is the end of
the
פסוק, pasuk, מדוע לא יבער הסנה. madua lo yivar hasneh. ולמחר לימא
וירא ה' כי סר לראות. U'l'machar leima Vayar Hashem ki sar lir'ot.
ולמחר, U'l'machar, the third day, ויאמר אל תקרב הלום. Vayomer al tikrav
halom. Okay, now again, it's interesting, right? Because they ask a question
on an incantation, and as a basis of their question, they revise
it, right? The third פסוק pasuk is better, I got another פסוק
pasuk that's better, so we'll use his פסוק pasuk for number three,
we'll combine the first two. Okay, וכי
פסיק ליה, v'ki fasik lei, and when you carve into this bush,
ליתתי, leitatei, you should go down close to the ground, bow down
and cut into it, ולימא הכי, v'leima hachi, and say the following:
הסנה הסנה, Hasneh hasneh, O bush, O bush, לאו משום דגביהת מכל
אילני אשרי הקדוש ברוך הוא שכינתיה עלך, lav mishum d'gavihat mikol ilanei
ashrei Hakadosh Baruch Hu shechintei alach, not because you were taller than
all the other trees did God choose to cause His divine presence
to dwell upon you. אלא משום דמככת מכל אילני אשרי קודשא בריך
הוא שכינתיה עלך, ella mishum d'mikhkat mikol ilanei ashrei Kudsha Brich Hu
shechintei alach, but because you were lower than all the trees,
the Holy One caused His presence to dwell upon you. וכי היכי
דחמיתיה אשתא לחנניה מישאל ועזריה, v'ki heichi d'chamitei eshta l'Hananya Mishael v'Azarya,
and in the same way the fire saw Hananya, Mishael, and Azarya
when they were thrown into the fire. furnace, וערקת מן קדמוהי v'arkat
min kadmohei and ran away from them, כן תחמינה אשתא לפלוני בר
פלונית ken tichmina eshta l'Ploni bar Plonis so the fire of the
fever meaning it should see פלוני Ploni the son of פלונית, Plonis,
you know, me the son of my mother, וערקת מן קדמוהי v'arkat
min kadmohei and run away from me.
Okay, so that's the end of that. Now again, I'm not exactly
sure what it has to do with God choosing the סנה Sneh
because it's the lowest of all the trees, with how that's related
to the incantation. What?
Seven cedars growing in the desert?
I under- no, no, that's also true. But I don't understand the
purpose of mentioning that for the sake of this incantation. Maybe I'm
so lowly, so God should have compassion on me, because you're making
yourself go low down, I don't know. Anyway, לסימטא l'simta for which-
cut off the bush? Yeah, you're cutting into it, maybe. I'm not
exactly sure what- anyway. For, which Rashi says is- what does Rashi
say is?
שחין, shechin, some type of a boils. לימא
הכי, leima hachi, say this: בז בזייה מס מסייה כס כסייה. baz
bazya mas masya kas kasya. Rashi doesn't even try to explain this.
This is just some type of a, you know, obviously doubling of
words. שרלי ואמרלי, sharli v'amarli, and now at somewhere we start having
actual names here. אילין מלאכי דאישתלחו מארעא דסדום. ilein malachei d'ishtalchu m'ara
d'Sdom. These are the angels that have been sent from the land
of Sodom. What? Explaining the-
I don't know. This is a לחש. lachash. Rashi says: ולא מסדום
בו. v'lo mi'Sdom bo. They didn't really come from Sodom. Anyway. ולאסיא
שחינתא דכאיבין, u'l'asya shechinta d'kaivin, and they should heal my painful boils.
Okay. No, I'm
sorry. ולאסיא- u'l'asya where does
it start? ולאסיא שחינתא
דכאיבין. u'l'asya shechinta d'kaivin. Okay. בזך ביזך בזבזך מס מסך כמון כמוך.
bazach bizach bazbazach mas masach kamon kamoch. Okay. Okay, so he keeps
on saying these various incantations. And then it says, עינייך ביך עינייך
ביך, einaich bich einaich bich, your appearance is to you, your appearance
is to you, meaning stay in your, you know, don't cause me
to inflame anymore, my skin to inflame, stay the way you are,
at least don't get worse. אשריכת בך, ashrichat bach, you should stay
in your place. Don't spread further on my body. זרעך ככלות וכפרדא
דלא פרה. zarach k'chlot u'ch'farda d'lo para. Your seed should be like
something that is held within, meaning not fruitful, and like a mule,
and like a donkey that דלא פרה ודלא רבייה, d'lo para v'dlo
ravya, that does not- you know, that is not fruitful and does
not multiply. כך לא תפרה ולא תרבה בגופיה דפלוני בר פלונית. kach
lo tifrei v'lo tirbei b'gufei d'Ploni bar Plonis. So you should not
be fruitful or multiply, you should not sort of spread on the
body of so-and-so the son of, you know, me the son of
my mother. So-and-so the son of so-and-so. Okay, so that's for boils.
לכיפא, l'kifa, which
Rashi also says is some type of a pus-filled boils or some
say that it's for a certain type of a shade, if a
demon has you. לימא הכי, leima hachi, say the following. חרב שלופה
וכלא נטושה, cherev shlufa v'chala netusha, a drawn sword and an extended
sling,
לא שמי יוחב חולין מכאובין. lo shmi yochav chulin machovin. Your name
should not be
of bad pains. Rashi says what in it? It's something about- one
minute. I just lost
the Rashi. Okay. לא שמי lo shmei should not be the name
of of bad pains. Rashi says what in it?
His name is not painful illnesses. Very good.
His name is not painful illnesses. Okay. לשידא, l'shida, for a shade,
another type of a shade. Rashi says maybe it's specifically a shade
of- hold on, is this the one Rashi said is the bathroom
shade or that's the next one? Next one. Thank you. Okay. לשידא
לימא, l'shida leima, for a shade, say, demon say,
הכי. hachi. הוויית דפקיק דפקוק הוויית. havayat d'pakik d'pakuk havayat. You were,
the דפקיק דפקוק d'pakik d'pakuk you were. I don't
know. ליטא תבור ומשומת. lita tavor u'mshumat. Cursed and broken and משומת,
mshumat, like a שמתא shamta in-
excommunicated, right. So that's- that's what you should be the shade. Okay.
בר טיט בר טמיא בר טינא. bar Tit bar Tamya bar Tina.
Again, calling it these various
names. טיט Tit is like plaster, טמיא Tamya is, טינא Tina also
I think is plaster. Anyway. כשמגז מרגיז ואיסטמאי. k'shmagaz margiz v'istamai. Okay.
And that's the rest of the incantation. Whatever that means. Rashi doesn't
try to explain it.
Okay. Right. Rashi says his name is בר טיט בר טינא, bar
Tit bar Tina, these are all his names. So you should be
broken and cursed and excommunicated. לשידא דבית הכיסא, l'shida d'veit hachisei, for
the shade of the bathroom. לימא הכי, leima hachi, say the following.
אקרקפי דארי, akarkafei d'ari, on the head of a lion... ואוסא דגוריאתא
v'a'usi d'guryaisa and on the nose of a female of a lioness,
אשכחתין לשדיא בר שירקאי ashkachton l'shida bar shirkai can be found the
shade, the demon of בר שירקאי bar shirkai פנדא panda במישרא דכרתי
b'meshera d'karti the whatever this is his name in the valley of
leeks, חבטיה chavtei or
בר שירקאי bar shirkai maybe it's בר שירקאי bar shirkai פנדא panda
that's his name במישרא דכרתי b'meshera d'karti in the valley of leeks,
חבטיה chavtei he should be he should be banged, בלועא דחמרא חתרתא
blu'a d'chamra chatartai and in the in the cheek of a donkey,
right, he should be right, that's true, that was the jawbone of
a right of an ass, right, it's the donkey, right, okay anyway,
so anyway he should be he should be you know hit or
banged, yes. So why are
I have banged him, yes go ahead.
Why is an individual talking to demons? Why don't we just pray
to God to have
you know, not only is that such a great question, but actually
we're going to read in about next three lines of the גמרא
Gemara that it's that it's forbidden to do incantations. Oh wow. I
didn't read ahead. So I will tell you, this is obviously a
very a very look you know, I mean if they believed, I
think it's actually good that to see the גמרות Gemaros where they
said, "Wait, this doesn't make sense, let's do it this way, let's
do it that way," which means that they didn't see it as
all total magic. They saw there was some thing that some type
of you know maybe this how they actually believed there was a
way to manipulate these forces
and therefore they could ask questions on it and revise it. So
it's not totally you know magic. But I don't know, I think
some practitioners of magic also believed that there was like a science
of the magic so they were actually using forces in the world.
So it is very strange you know, but it was extremely widespread.
Look, we all know the רמב"ם Rambam that you know says of
course this was all nonsense you know, I read to you a
few days ago and we're actually about to come up to it
about the whole issue about the קמיעס, kameios, you know where the
רמב"ם Rambam says it's all nonsense and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
says you can quoting the רמב"ם Rambam that you can say an
incantation of somebody on שבת Shabbos because it's psychologically beneficial and the
גר"א Gra says it's all based on the רמב"ם Rambam who was
misled by Greek philosophers and we all know that the incantations really
work and they're very prevalent in the גמרא, Gemara, you know. So
there was actually right the rationalists versus the you know anti-rationalists or
the a-rationalists at least.
Yes.
It might be the same answer but let me elucidate. What what
what are we supposed to make of this?
What are we supposed I don't know I
mean were were people on a higher level then you can actually
No, that's not how I would interpret this. No, they did have
these guys are crazy.
Well, they're not crazy.
You cannot look you know, it's very arrogant to it's very arrogant
to judge people in the past based on limited science you know.
We only people are limited by the science.
Are these are these
told Well, the what right, so that is a good point. So
okay alright, so that is a good point. So for some for
some people it's very important to say the rabbis never made any
mistakes even when they talked about science, even when they talked about
incantations, because if you allow for the fact that they made mistakes,
then how can we trust them about הלכה halacha and about everything
else? The רמב"ם Rambam you know very much says not that way.
He says, "Look, they we cannot have expected them to have have
a
they weren't scientists, b they were not more advanced than the scientists
of their days." And how could you expect them to know more
than the scientists of their days? That's not where their greatness as
religious authorities comes, that somehow God reveals to them you know what
the future of science is going to be. So they were limited
by that, but their greatness comes as you know as those who
pass down the tradition and as those who you know were authorized
to interpret what the תורה Torah says. So you don't have to
see that it's all one package you know. You don't have to
think that they were able to be wiser than you know than
any knowledge of their time.
So there's some stuff in the גמרא Gemara like this. Is it
religion?
No, I actually think at that time Right, we now live in
a time of science, so we see something like this and we
want to say you know besides first of all what type of
empirical test did they do to see that it worked, but we
also want to say, "What are the scientific principles? This cannot be
explained by any scientific principles and therefore it has to be false."
Fine, we're living post-the you know
the enlightenment. You know, in the earlier times they did not have
a well-worked out sense of like the scientific principles that they could
say that this obviously is not logical and doesn't make sense. And
people deal with illness, they have no sense of control over the
illness, so you know develop these ways of trying to feel that
you can control these things.
But that was my scientific question, I'm not criticizing them for not
being scientists, I'm asking is this religious-based or this just sort
of like a No, I think they're just telling you good advice.
They're not this is very this is very not problematic when they're
just telling you, "Hey, here's a good way to heal a problem,"
you know. It's like they're just giving you some advice. Not a
מצוה. mitzvah. No no no no. In this גמרא Gemara it is
not in a הלכה halacha context at all. The problem is when
these types of statements inform הלכה. halacha. So when for example example
like we learned the other day when
And weren't we told even the times of the גאונים Geonim to
disregard their medical advice?
Yes, the גאונים Geonim over, thank you, the גאונים Geonim already said
that you, you know, you cannot go by the medical recommendations in
the גמרא. Gemara.
So how can we have a problem today with saying don't worry
about this
science if the גאונים Geonim did it? Right. Well, I will say
that the פרום frum answer to that is, so there's three responses
to how do you deal with the fact that the גמרא Gemara
seems to, what it says clearly contradicts our knowledge and experience. So
one answer is, no, we're wrong, they got it right, somehow we,
we don't understand, okay, and it actually still works if somehow I
don't know if we knew how to do it or something like
that. The second answer is no, no, no, that's not what we,
that doesn't work today, but,
you know, the רמב"ם Rambam answer would be, the less פרום frum
answer is, פרום frum quote unquote, but, you know, they weren't scientists,
it's not a big deal, so they got it wrong. Then the
third answer says yes, you're right, the facts are not as they
describe it, this doesn't work today, but it's not because they got
it wrong, it's because נשתנה הטבע nishtana hateva the laws of nature
have changed, and that's why we don't have to deny what we
directly observe that this stuff doesn't work, but God forbid we should
suggest that they got it wrong, it's really just the way the
world works and nature works has changed over time. Okay, so yes,
that's a quick little summary of how to deal with, you know,
contradictions between science and הלכה halakha and when the, or when the
רבנים Rabbanim say, you know, sort of deal with these types of
healings and incantations. Okay, let's finish this up, this discussion, ובני מלכים
בזוגין u'vnei melakhim be'zugin and sons of princes, like very important people,
can wear these like bells.
מאן תנא Man tanna who is the תנא? tanna? אמר רבי יהושע,
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, and then it says really anybody can, but they
talked about the common person, which was, you know, the common taste,
which was when it was done by princes. So אמר רבי יהושע
רבי שמעון היא, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, Rabbi Shimon hi, it's רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, דאמר כל ישראל בני מלכים הן. de'amar kol Yisrael bnei
melakhim hen. All of ישראל Yisrael are sons of kings, which means
that, you know, meaning we're all descended from אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham
Yitzchak v'Yaakov, and therefore, you know, these types of, you know, whatever's
appropriate by important people is appropriate to us as well, so if
it could be worn by princes, it could be worn by us.
But that doesn't work for the איסורא דשבת. issura d'Shabbos.
I know, so it's just interesting why the גמרא Gemara needs this
explanation. Anyway, also because א a גמרא Gemara says שבת Shabbos and
it shouldn't be a חשש chashash of taking it off could be,
so what if you make that statement if the reality is that
those aren't the social norms. Number two, פשיטא דאורייתא pshita d'Oraita question
the גמרא Gemara says, you know, even wearing clothes of somebody, as
long as they're within the same gender, wearing clothes of somebody who's
completely like a, you know, different class than you is still considered
clothes. So it's not exactly clear how that statement is functioning here.
רבא אמר באריג בכסותה ודברי הכל Rava amar b'arig bi'ksusa v'divrei hakol
it's woven into your garment, so therefore everybody could agree because if
it's woven into your garment, there's no concern that you'll take it
off. And therefore even if it's a little unusual, we're not concerned
for you to be wearing it, we're not concerned you'll take it
off. Okay, we end this פרק perek with all of these fascinating
issues about clothing and all the things that we saw and I'll
just remind us of, by the way, the two important things we
saw the other day, one is that all these things you're not
supposed to wear because you're afraid you'll take it off, and רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, תוספות Tosafot pointed out, and that nowadays everybody wears
this, all the women wear the jewelry and so on, and he
gave three answers all three answers which were repeated in the שלחן
ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Number one is that, that
maybe we rule like the opinion that you can wear it in
a חצר, chatzer, which he would say would mean even without an
עירוב eiruv a חצר chatzer as long as it's not a רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, and arguing that nowadays there's no, we don't have
a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim anymore, which is a position that we
rely on to make an עירוב. eiruv. So that's one explanation. Second
explanation is that, yeah, everybody is sinning but it's only rabbinic, it's
not biblical, so and they're not going to listen to us if
we try to, if we try to tell them otherwise, so better
to keep our peace. מוטב יהיו שוגגין. mutav yehyu shogegin. And the
third answer which I find is the most interesting is that all
these things, even though they're said in absolute terms, at least in
this case, were only meant in a context where there's a concern
that people will actually take it off and show. And nowadays that
that's not the social context that because they're common or whatever people
don't do that, none of these things apply. So that's א a
just a little reminder about everything we've been learning all the rabbinic
stuff and the concern you'll take it off and show somebody is
was not practiced and there are three explanations given. The other important
thing I want to remind you of as we go into this
last משנה mishnah to end the פרק perek was what we said
yesterday, which was talking about wearing a false leg, a wooden leg,
for somebody that's amputated and the גמרא Gemara there talks about things
that are attached to the body,
and actually has some concerns about some of them, maybe they're not
considered like clothing, maybe you'll drop it and you'll come to carry
it, not exactly clear what the concerns were, but nevertheless תוספות Tosafot
makes an argument and it's extremely important because it gets פסק'ן pasken
להלכה l'halakha that all of that was assuming that these things were
not needed, were not strictly were not really needed to walk. But
anything that's really needed to walk even if it is not worn,
even if it's held, like crutches or like a cane, if you
could not walk without it, he says is considered to be part
of the body. Body and not carrying, and we actually rule that
way. And that's extremely important in places where there's no עירוב *eruv*
to allow things like crutches and canes and wheelchairs. So that was
a very important, you know, I would say probably the most important
part of, you know, I don't know, the most, whatever, anyway, because
we're also a little oblivious to a lot of this because we
have, because we just have the עירובס *eruvs*. But certainly a very
critical part was that issue. I mean, also everything that's for medical
purposes are not a problem, you know, on the body and are
actively functioning on the body. But again, the crutches is a much
bigger חידוש *chiddush*, and that comes from תוספות *Tosafos* we saw yesterday.
Now we end with a last משנה Mishna *mishna*, which gets to
the theme we've just been on and the theme we touched on
when we dealt with קמיעס *kameias* with the amulets, which is various
things that are worn again for medical purposes, but maybe ones that
don't make too much sense to us. It seems a little bit
more superstitious. So let's take a look at the משנה Mishna, *mishna*.
יוצאים בביצת החרגול *Yotzin be-veitzat ha-chargol*, you can go out wearing around
you an egg from a certain type of a of a like
a locust or grasshopper.
What do they describe it's called there, חרגול *chargol*? Yeah, okay, fine.
I mean, it's one of the things listed in the תורה Torah.
*Torah*. ובשן שועל *u-ve-shen shu'al*, the tooth of a fox, ובמסמר מן
הצלוב *u-ve-masmer min ha-tzaluv*, and and a nail from somebody who's been
crucified. Jesus wasn't the only one crucified. Romans crucified everybody there that
they were sort of execute. And if you take a nail from
a crucifixion, that was seen as having some type of medicinal powers.
משום רפואה refuah *mishum refuah*, you can wear it because these are
for health purposes. And again, something worn on the body that's serving
a health purpose as you're wearing is not considered carrying. דברי רבי
מאיר *divrei Rabbi Meir*, that's what Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אוסרים *va-Chachamim
osrin*, the Rabbis forbid it, אף בחול *af be-chol*, even during the
weekday, משום דרכי האמורי darchei emori *mishum darchei ha-Emori*, because of the
ways of the Amorites, because of the ways, you know, one of
the seven Canaanite nations. Now, let's first read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
describing what these do, and then the rest of the focus will
be on דרכי אמורי darchei emori *darchei Emori*. יוצאים בביצת החרגול *Yotzin
be-veitzat ha-chargol*, the egg of the locust, דעבדי לשיחלא *de-avdi le-shichla*, you
use it for שיחלא *shichla*. רש״י *Rashi* says an earache. ובשן של
שועל *u-ve-shen shel shu'al*, hey, what do you call it? A fox
tooth, דעבדי לשינתא *de-avdi le-shinnata*, you use it for sleeping purposes. דחיה
*de-chaya*, if it is from a live fox, למאן דניים *le-man de-nayim*,
then it would be used for somebody that is, you know, sleeping
too much. דמיתה *de-mita*, right, and for one of a dead fox,
למאן דלא ניים *le-man de-la nayim*, for a person who can't fall
asleep. Okay.
ובמסמר מן הצלוב *u-ve-masmer min ha-tzaluv*,
the nail from the crucifix, דעבדי לזירפא *de-avdi le-zirpa*, that
you use it for זירפא *zirpa*, which רש״י *Rashi* says is some
type of like a of a of a swollen, not swollen, infected
wound, particularly he says from metal, so maybe it's what do you
get from metal, the tetanus? Tetanus, yeah. All right. Okay. So that's
it. So now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this, משום רפואה
refuah, דברי רבי מאיר *mishum refuah divrei Rabbi Meir*. So אביי Abaye
ורבא v'Rava. דאמרי תרווייהו *Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarvaihu*, now we're going to
get into the issue of דרכי אמורי darchei emori. *darchei Emori*. Now
an interesting thing about דרכי אמורי darchei emori, *darchei Emori* is that
this is a recurring theme in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, is this
משום דרכי אמורי darchei emori? *mishum darchei Emori*, not משום דרכי אמורי
darchei emori *mishum darchei Emori*? It doesn't tell you exactly what the
prohibition of דרכי אמורי darchei emori. *darchei Emori* is. דרכי אמורי darchei
emori. *darchei Emori* means ways of the Amorites, ways of the כנענים
*Kena'anim*, ways of the non-Jews, let's say more generically. So it's mentioned
in two other tannaitic sources. First of all, in the ספרא Sifra
*Sifra*, you know, the tannaitic source on ויקרא *Vayikra*, where it says
at the end of אחרי מות *Acharei Mos*, ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו *u-ve-chukoteihem
lo telechu*, do not go in their ways, in the ways of
the nations of Canaan, okay, or the ways of Mitzrayim. כמעשה ארץ
מצרים אשר *ke-ma'aseh eretz Mitzrayim asher*, you know, לא תעשו *lo ta'asu*
וכמעשה ארץ כנען אשר אני מביא אתכם שמה *u-ke-ma'aseh eretz Kena'an asher
ani meivi etchem shama* what does it something לא תעשו *lo ta'asu*
ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו *u-ve-chukoteihem lo telechu*. So don't go in the ways
of Mitzrayim, don't go in the ways of Canaan. So it actually
says, what does it mean, don't go in the ways of Mitzrayim
and Canaan? Does it mean like you can't, you know, you know,
do like the normal types of things that they do? No, it
means things that are specific for them. So one example it gives
is a very famous example is קרקסאות ותיאטראות *kirkasa'ot ve-te'atra'ot*, circuses and
theaters. Now that is particularly though because in the Roman world, circuses
and theaters were very much to the gods. And that had a
very, even though you were going and you were just having a
good time, but it was dedicated to the gods and it had
an עבודה זרה avodah zarah *avoda zara* framing to it. So that's
number one. And then it says, there's another opinion in there that
says אלו דרכי האמורי darchei emori. שמנו חכמים *elu darchei ha-Emori she-manu
Chachamim*. These are, what does it mean ובחוקותיהם לא תלכו *u-ve-chukoteihem lo
telechu*, the Amorite ways that the חכמים *Chachamim* have listed. Which means,
interestingly, just in terms of, you know, sort of Talmudic history, that
there has been an, there was a list called דרכי אמורי darchei
emori. *darchei Emori*, practices we don't do, you know, non-Jewish superstitious practices
we don't do. And they, nobody really bothered articulating exactly why it
was prohibited. So one תנא tana *tanna* says, oh, because it's ובחוקותיהם
*u-ve-chukoteihem*, you're not supposed to go in the ways of the non-Jews.
The list actually appears quite extensively in the תוספתא Tosefta *Tosefta*. We're
going to see it somewhat referred to in a minute. And there
it also says, this is דרכי אמורי darkei Emori. *darchei Emori*, this
is דרכי אמורי darkei Emori, *darchei Emori*, this isn't דרכי אמורי darkei
Emori *darchei Emori*, this is דרכי אמורי darkei Emori *darchei Emori*. דרכי
אמורי darkei Emori. biggest two chapters of תוספתא Tosefta, of listing. So
if you're interested in what type of ancient practices were done, you
could go look at that תוספתא, Tosefta, yeah, פרק Perek seven and
eight in the תוספתא, Tosefta six and seven depending on which version
you have, on שבת, Shabbat, in שבת. Shabbat. And then in the
middle of there somewhere it starts talking about this is prohibited because
of לא תעוננו, lo teonenu, לא תנחשו. lo senachashu. You know, there's
specific things about like foretelling the future, divination, magic, where it starts
specifically says don't do these things. And then it relates to specific
practices that fall into like divination and magic. And you know, דרכי
אמורי darkei Emori sort of is like this huge umbrella category of
all the types of things that are like forbidden, but it's not
always clear exactly what prohibition certain things on the list. The biggest
generic prohibition is בחוקותיהם, bechukoseihem, not to go in the ways of
the non-Jews, but some of them actually are more specifically prohibited as
like divination and magic and so on, which are specific לאוין lavin
in the תורה. Torah Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara just describing what's on that list and not on the
list. So it says like this.
It's so confusing.
I know it is. So let's look at the גמרא. Gemara אביי
ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye veRava de'amri tarvaihu, Abaye and Rava both say,
כל דבר שיש בו משום רפואה, kol davar sheyeish bo mishum refuah,
אין בו משום דרכי אמורי. ein bo mishum darchei emori. Anything that
really has health benefits is not דרכי אמורי. darkei Emori. Then it's
not, you know, it's not magic or it's not whatever, it's not
idolatrous. It really is effective. Like all the incantations we just said
before. So right, or like and maybe that's what's being debated in
the משנה Mishnah. about the fox tooth. Is that really effective or
not really effective? Right, the רמב"ם Rambam on the פירוש המשניות Peirush
HaMishnayos said how do you know if יש בו משום רפואה? yeish
bo mishum refuah? Well, you look and see if it works. So
if it works, it's not דרכי אמורי, Darkei Emori, it's a real
medicinal. Now, but interestingly let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes because
you would have said now you can understand how we'd had all
these incantations. What about דרכי אמורי? Darkei Emori They thought that they
had observed it working, you know, maybe that would be an explanation.
But let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes, very interesting place with
this. It says האי אין בו משום רפואה יש בו משום דרכי
אמורי? hai ein bo mishum refuah yeish bo mishum darchei emori? Are
you telling me that if it's not, you know, healing, then it
is a דרכי אמורי Darkei Emori. problem? והתניא, vehatanya, it was taught
in a ברייתא, Baraisa, אילן שמשיר פירותיו, ilan shemashir peirosav, if you
have a tree that is dropping its fruit, how do you, what
do you do to fix the problem? סוקרו בסיקרא, sokro besikra, you
sort of paint it with some type of a paint like that's
very you know, וטוענו באבנים, vetoano be'avanim, and you laden it down
with rocks on the branches. So בשלמא bishlama וטוענו באבנים vetoano be'avanim
I understand why ladening it down with the branches works. כי היכי
דליכחוש חילה ki heichi delich-chush cheilah in order that its strength should
be weakened, maybe because somehow the sap is going too strong, it's
causing the fruit to drop, so somehow there's some physical sort of
effect that these rocks will have that will counteract that and make
it not drop the fruit. That I can explain. אלא ela סוקרו
בסיקרא, sokro besikra, to paint it, מאי רפואה קעביד? mai refuah ka'avid?
What type of good is that doing? How is that medicinal? How
is that helping? So the גמרא Gemara says כי היכי, ki heichi,
so the גמרא Gemara has an answer. You know, here's how it
works. כי היכי דליחזייה איניש וליבעי עליה רחמי, ki heichi delichzeih inish
veliv-ei aleih rachamei, people should see it and should pray for its
benefit. They see obviously you're painting it, that means that there's a
problem, and they say oh נבך, nebech, this guy's tree, so they
pray for you and your trees get better. כדתניא, kedetanya, like we
taught in the ברייתא, Baraisa, וטמא טמא יקרא, vetamei tamei yikra, the
מצורע metzora calls out, I am טמא, tamei, I am טמא. tamei.
צריך להודיע צערו לרבים. tzarich lehodiya tza'aro lerabbim. So you could say
other people call it out, but the פסוק pasuk says no, even
the מצורע metzora calls it out. Let people know about your pain,
ורבים יבקשו עליו רחמים, verabbim yevakshu alav rachamim, and people will pray
for you that the צרה tzarah should clear up. So here too
people will pray for you. Now what I find very fascinating about
the גמרא Gemara is if the question of יש בו משום רפואה
yeish bo mishum refuah is does it seem to work, then what
type of question is it? Well, how was this painting it doing
any good? I don't know, but it works, right, like all these
incantations. The fact that the גמרא Gemara asks this question means that
it's saying that we have to understand how it works. It has
to make sense. There has to be some rational explanation. And I
can't understand how the painting makes sense and wants to call it
דרכי אמורי. Darkei Emori. Well, if that's true, well, that's very consistent
with us. Like we said, well, anything that can't be explained by
science, well, that's all nonsense. Great! So then everything we've been saying
until now is דרכי אמורי. Darkei Emori. You know, so it's really
I don't get it, like how did it allow all of this
stuff. Now again, this is the משנה, Mishnah this is a different
conversation. You know, maybe you could say that different גמרות Gemoras have
a different take. The רמב"ם Rambam says that the גמרא Gemara assumed
anything that they thought that they had evidence of worked would be
in the רפואה refua. category, not the דרכי אמורי. Darkei Emori, But
that, and that could explain you could allow a lot of these
crazy stuff and incantations because you think that it's effective. But but
again, you know, the fact that the גמרא Gemara asks the question
it does, sounds like the גמרא Gemara has a much smaller category
of what's רפואה, refua only things that we can explain, not just
things that we think actually have seen that works. Yes.
Ah, two things. One is I'm a little worried about this make
sense thing because there are a lot of things that when they
were first proposed by scientists didn't make any sense whatsoever, then we
discovered that the wild and crazy scientists turned out to be right.
Right, and that's an excellent point too, because the more, the better
approach from a scientific perspective is not just things that fit into
our current theory, but actually the sort of empirical approach. Let's actually,
you know, see what works and see what doesn't and, you know,
even if we don't understand it right now. It is interesting I
mentioned the other day when we did had some discussion I think
around the קמיעות kameas and about, you know, פוסקים poskim dealing with,
with various, you know, healing things that they couldn't explain and do
you allow חילול שבת chilul shabbos for them if you, you know,
people say that they work but they don't make any sense is
the whole issue about the approach towards, you know, the Western approach
towards, like, what is it, the Eastern medicines, like, what? Acupuncture.
Yeah,
alternative medicine, acupuncture, acupressure. So you know, right, like I think now
some, you know, insurances or some insurances at least are do cover
it, but for a long time, you know, insurance no insurance would
cover it and, you know, Western doctors and science would like scoff
at it, right, because they couldn't explain it. But, you know, the
reality is that it seems like that these things are actually evidenced
that it's effective.
And now maybe coming up with some explanations that make sense. And
now maybe coming up with some explanations. So right, the actually the
more scientific thing is to go by the evidence and not by
what seems to make sense. So again, it is quite fascinating that
the גמרא Gemara. is seen to now say that it's only things
that make sense are okay. Yes.
And the second thing, this looks like it's evidence that you can
pray for, for the welfare of a non-human living creature.
No, I think actually somebody owns the tree. But I'm sure you
could anyway, but I think the idea is, who's the person bothering
painting and putting the stones on it? The person who doesn't want
to lose his fruit. So yes, so why all of
a sudden we're having a problem with the ביצת החרגול beitzat hachargol
and now with the other things we had before?
That's why I said. Who doesn't explain it? If you think that
then you start asking questions about everything before. But look, not every
גמרא Gemara, is, you know, is one unit written by the same
person. You know, this was a lot of discussion about אביי Abaye
and רב פפא Rav Pappa and whatever. This is a discussion here
about, well actually it is אביי Abaye, ורבא. v'Rava So it actually
is problematic because this is אביי, Abaye you know, אביי Abaye was
a big speaker before so
you can't say that they're totally different people
here, אמוראים Amoraim that are dealing with the issue. I mean, that
would be one way of dealing with it. Not every גמרא Gemara,
has to agree with every other גמרא. Gemara But anyway, but it
is the גמרא, Gemara the סתם stam of the גמרא, Gemara not
אביי Abaye ורבא explicitly that are framing it this way, that it's
something that makes sense rather than something that's been tested. אביי could
have said it's based on what's been tested and he thought that
all the incantations actually have been tested and work, but the סתם
stam of the גמרא Gemara assumes a much narrower definition. Yes.
One of the jobs I had on קיבוץ kibbutz was painting trees.
Really? For what purpose?
We did that because they,
it
apparently keeps the, the moisture in. It keeps the moisture in! You
see? So there you go. The גמרא Gemara had an explanation. There
was an explanation. The גמרא Gemara just didn't get it. Okay, yeah.
I'm just thinking what the גמרא Gemara means. I think you have
to address there's a glaring logical fallacy here that something needs to
be added to give us some context. Right? It's like if A
then B doesn't mean if B then or not B then A
or something, right? In other words, when it says הא אין בו
משום רפואה יש בו משום דרכי האמורי, ha ein bo mishum refua
yesh bo mishum darchei emori, that's not implied by the first statement
unless there's a piece missing in the statement like in what category
are we talking.
Right, right, we're not talking, right, you can do a lot of
דרכי האמורי darchei emori that's not, that's not attempting to be part
of רפואה. Right, right, it means, right, that's a good point. It
means within the category of trying to, you know, heal, so if
you, it's proven to be רפואה but that's right, it's not like
in the world of different types of things you could do. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara, continues. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina,
כמאן תלינן כוסטא בדקלא, ke-man talinan kusta be-dikla, according to whom do
we hang, you know, dates on a palm tree that apparently palm
tree that's not producing or that's producing or that's dropping its fruit?
כי האי תנא. Ki hai tana. Okay, like the תנא tana that
we taught before, which is the one about, you know, that you
do it so people see and pray for it and so on.
תני תנא בפרק אמוראי קמיה דרבי חייא בר
אבין. Tani tana be-perek Amorai kamei de-Rabbi Chiya bar Abin. So the
תנא tana taught in the chapters of the אמוראים Amoraim in the
presence of רבי חייא בר אבין. Rabbi Chiya bar Abin. So what's
the chapters of the אמוראים? Amoraim? So רש"י Rashi says these are
the two chapters of the תוספתא Tosefta that is this big list
of what is דרכי האמורי. darchei emori And as I said before,
the fact that it's being referred to in the ספרא shows that
this was like an old list of what is דרכי האמורי and,
you know, again without a clear explication of A, what criteria are
we using and B, exactly what איסור issur it is, presumably it's
at least בחוקותיהם. be-chukoteihem. So anyway the תנא tana taught, here's some
of the teachings that that תנא taught about what's in the דרכי
האמורי list. אמר ליה, Amar leh,
so anyway he taught, he taught this in front of רבי חייא
בר אבין. Rabbi Chiya bar Abin. So you know, the question is
if you have a list, this יש yesh or אין בו משום
דרכי האמורי, ein bo mishum darchei emori, this אין בו ein bo
משום דרכי האמורי, this יש בו משום דרכי האמורי, yesh bo mishum
darchei emori, so there could be a big question like what the
text is. Should this be אין ein or יש? yesh? You know,
those things could get confused, right? If, so he said, so רב
חייא בר אבין Rav Chiya bar Abin said to him, כולהו אית
בהו משום דרכי האמורי לבר מהני. kulu is bo mishum darchei emori
levar mi-hani. That entire list is all in the אסור assur category,
it's all יש בו דרכי האמורי yesh bo darchei emori except for
these. No, no, no, everything in the תוספתא Tosefta, is in the
דרכי אמורי. darkei emori, The only two that are not in the
דרכי אמורי, darkei emori. that’s אין בו משום דרכי אמורי, ein bo
mishum darkei Emori, is the following two. מי שיש לו עצם בגרונו,
mi she-yesh lo etzem begrono, if you get a bone caught in
your throat, מביא
מאותו המין, mevi me-oto ha-min, you take from the same species like
if it’s a chicken bone you take a chicken or a chicken
another chicken bone, ומניח ליה על קדקדו, u-maniach lei al kadkado, put
it on his forehead, ולימא הכי, v'leima hachi, and say the following:
חד חד נחית בלע, chad chad nachis bala, one by one go
down and swallow, בלע נחית חד חד, bala nachis chad chad, swallow
and go down one by one. So it's an incantation, instead of
the Heimlich maneuver. Okay, אין בו משום דרכי אמורי, ein bo mishum
darkei Emori, that's not a problem. Now again what's fascinating is that
this is something you were you would have expected something that wouldn't
have had an incantation. The fact that it has an incantation for
us it immediately says, oh that's not the type of thing that
we were talking about before that logically makes sense, but again now
we're saying that things could be not דרכי אמורי even with incantations
presumably because they've been proven and that seems to be sufficient. So
it's no longer about logically making sense presumably, unless they thought they
had some logical explanation here, yes.
It's a passage about speaking from the spices.
Yeah, right, right, right. Oh and we’re going actually actually we’re going
to come up to that so don’t worry. Now that's number one
is okay, number two that's okay is לאידרא, le-idra, for idra, which
is also רש"י Rashi says like a fishbone is caught, לימא הכי,
leima hachi, we'd say the following: ננעצתא כמחט, nin'atzta ke-makat, you are
stuck like a needle, ננעלתא כתריס, nin'alta ke-tris, you are locked like
a like a shutter, שיע שיע, shia shia, go down, go down,
and that and that is not a problem. So these two
incantations are okay. So again, you know, what about all the incantations
we just said earlier today? Again so I don't know and again
I don't know whether we’re assuming it has to be logically explained
or just believed to be proven. The רמב"ם Rambam again says that
these were things that they thought that they had proven. Now I
will say interestingly so if you actually look at the תוספתא, Tosefta
so there's a couple things that there are said אין ein בו
are okay. This says here רב חייא בר אבין Rav Chiya bar
Avin said everything is a problem except these two, but in the
תוספתא Tosefta there's a lot of debates in the ראשונים Rishonim about
different texts and versions of the תוספתא Tosefta where certain things are
in the okay category or the not okay category. So it's so
it's clear why he’s trying to say I believe everything is in
the not okay category except for these two.
What about tying the red string around you?
I don't know. האומר, ha-omer, so now the גמרא Gemara says, I
will say the following that the יראים, Yere'im, רבי אליעזר ממיץ, Rabbi
Eliezer mi-Metz, a תלמיד talmid of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that
these are the things that the חז"ל Chazal at that time knew
were the מעשי ארץ כנען ma'asei eretz Kna'an of maybe even of
the time of the תורה and he says אסור להוסיף עליהן, assur
le-hosif aleihen, you can't add to the list. So anything not on
the list is מותר. mutar.
So that's at least what the יראים Yere'im says. האומר ha-omer גד
גדי, gad gadi, the person who says let my luck increase, וסנוק
לו, u-snuk lo, and not be tired, actually people know at the
beginning of פסחים Pesachim that comes up, אשקיי ובושקיי, ashkei u-bushkei, day
and night, יש בו משום דרכי אמורי, yesh bo mishum darkei Emori,
that's a particular sort of incantation, you know, and therefore it's a
דרכי אמורי problem.
We say it on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
Yeah, well you don't say this exact language, presumably it's not just
a prayer that you want to have fortune.
Well I don't I don't mean the prayer, I mean when we
have the like the pomegranate and all those.
Where you say יהי רצון. yehi ratzon. Right, but that’s a prayer
to God, may it be your will God so and so. So
this no, so this is particularly well you could read it as
a prayer like God may my luck whatever, but it seems like
it's a very specific incantation. Okay so that's why it's yes.
What language is that? Aramaic?
Well the yeah וסנוק לו אשקיי ובושקיי, u-snuk lo ashkei u-bushkei, yeah
that's a good question. I mean it's it seems Aramaic. גד גדי
gad gadi is more biblical. אשקיי ובושקיי ashkei u-bushkei I have no
idea I assume it's Aramaic and וסנוק לו u-snuk lo grammatically it's
Aramaic. So yeah it seems to be the end of it is
Aramaic. So רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer גד gad אינו אלא
לשון עבודה זרה. eino ela lashon avodah zarah. גד, gad, not G-O-D,
but גד gad גימל דלת, gimmel dalet, is actually a name of
of of another god. שנאמר she-ne'emar העורכים לגד שלחן, ha-orchim l'Gad shulchan,
those that lay out their table to the to the god Gad.
So so so therefore actually it’s worse than simple דרכי אמורי. It
has עבודה זרה avodah zarah maybe you’re not thinking about the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah but actually it incorporates certain real עבודה זרה avodah
zarah. language in it. It's quite fascinating that one of the שבטים
shevatim Gad is a name of an עבודה זרה. avoda zara We're
actually going to see another one in a minute. הוא בשמו והיא
בשמה, hu b'shmo v'hi b'shmah, let's say husband and wife somehow in
the bedroom say that they’re going to call each other by one
another’s name, יש בו משום דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum darkei Emori.
That is also some type of דרכי אמורי doing that. דונו דוני,
donu doni, let my let my barrels be strengthened, יש בו משום
דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum darkei Emori. So you’re concerned about your
wine, that's a type of incantation of דרכי אמורי. רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer אין דן, ein dan, the fact that you’re using
the language of דן dan and doubling it’s like גד גדי gad
gadi דונו דוני, donu doni, right, אין דן אלא. ein dan ela.
That's really worse than just דרכי אמורי, it's not just superstition, it's
actually evoking, you know it has vestiges of עבודה זרה avoda zara.
in it, שנאמר shenemar הנשבעים באשמת שומרון ואמרו חי אלהיך דן, ha-nishba'im
be-ashmat Shomron ve-amru chai elohecha Dan, those that take swear in the
sort of sin of שומרון, Shomron, the false god, ואמר חי אלהיך
דן, ve-amar chai elohecha Dan, live your god דן. Dan. So דן
Dan is a name of a god. So it's actually quite interesting
that two of the names of the שבטים, shevatim, גד Gad and
דן Dan are, you know, are actually names of עבודה זרה. avoda
zara, I mean these were names that came later. What? Well, I
don't know, maybe.
That's a possibility, but
isn't דן Dan the tribe of part of שומרון Shomron that actually
refers to the story or the people in דן? Dan?
Well,
that's a good point. And the idol was in דן. Dan. One
of the two golden calves were put up in דן. Dan. Right.
So it's actually true, it's an interesting way of reading the פסוק.
pasuk. So, you know, also, I mean talking about like what words
in our language that are from עבודה זרה, you know, תמוז Tammuz
which is a name of a god, as it says מבכות את
התמוז, mevakkot et ha-Tammuz, right? So
anyway, why'd he do that? האומר לעורב, Ha-omer la-orev, somebody that says
to the raven, צרח, tzrach, screech, like you're concerned about some something
like hearing the raven maybe made you feel that it's a portent
of something bad, so you say screech, ולאורבתא, u-le-orveta, the female raven,
צרחי, tzrichi, also like screech, והחזירי לי זנבך לטובה, ve-hachiziri li zenavech
le-tova, and turn your tail to me for good, יש בו משום
דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum Darkei Emori.
That's a דרכי אמורי problem. האומר שחטו תרנגול זה שקרא ערבית, Ha-omer
shachtu tarnegol ze she-kara arvit,
slaughter this rooster that called out ערבית, arvit, you know, cause roosters
are only supposed to crow in the morning before it gets dark,
not after it gets dark, ותרנגולת שקראה גברית, ve-tarnegolet she-kar'ah gavrit, and
a hen that called out גברית, gavrit, right? Because it either could
mean in the morning, or it could mean, no, רש"י Rashi doesn't
say in the morning, I think somebody else says, anyway, but גברית
gavrit like a גבר, gever, like a rooster, the hen that called
out like a rooster, יש בו משום דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum
Darkei Emori. The fact that you feel you have to slaughter it,
you know, or else something bad will happen, again, it's like, you
know, now of course I don't know how many of you, you
know, had Jewish mothers or grandmothers, you know, that would do say
something, throw the salt behind the back, you know, all these types
of things you do to, oh my gosh, to prevent something bad
from happening. So here's the same type of thing. Something went wrong,
what do you do? You slaughter the rooster. Right? We'll kill the
old red rooster when she comes. So anyway, so all of these
like a lot of superstition seems to be דרכי אמורי. You understand
why the יראים Yereim said you can't add to the list because
you know then you'd have to lose a lot of good Jewish
superstitions. Anyway, okay. אשתה ואותיר אשתה ואותיר, eshteh ve-otir eshteh ve-otir, I
will drink and leave over, drink and leave over, יש בו משום
דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum Darkei Emori. Now that's right. I mean
some people דוקא, davka, you know, they leave over at the end
of the meal, ושבענו והותרנו, ve-savanu ve-hotarnu, but you know maybe again
it's the fact that you specifically say it like as an incantation,
you know, maybe there's you understand, you know, there's a nice idea
there, but the incantation part makes it דרכי אמורי. המפקעת ביצים בכותל,
Ha-mafka'at beitzim ba-kotel, if you sort of crack eggs against the wall,
or רש"י Rashi says stick eggshells on a wall, that's another way
of reading it, בפני אפרוחים, bifnei efrochim, in front of the chicks,
and this was somehow done to make the, as a some type
of a belief that it would make the chicks live, you know,
because you wouldn't, didn't want your chicks to die, so יש בו
משום דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum Darkei Emori. That's a forbidden Amorite
practice. המגיס בפני אפרוחים, Ha-megis bifnei efrochim, if you stir like a
pot in front of chicks, again, in front of chicks, again, this
was done because of a concern that the chicks would die, יש
בו משום דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum Darkei Emori. That's a problem.
המרקדת, Ha-merakkedet, if you dance, והמונה שבעים ואחד אפרוחים, ve-ha-monah shiv'im ve-echad
efrochim, and count seventy-one chicks, this would again, you know, apparently it
was a real anxiety, you have all these chicks you're afraid they're
going to die, so they would do different things that they would
think would protect them, so one would be a dance with counting
seventy-one chicks, בשביל שלא ימותו, bishvil she-lo yamutu, here it's explicit, so
they shouldn't die, יש בו משום דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum Darkei
Emori. Now, somebody else talked about making spices or whatever. המרקדת לכותח,
Ha-merakkedet le-kutach, you're dancing when you're making your כותח, kutach, which was
your sour milk yogurty dip, והמשתקת לעדשים, ve-ha-meshattaka le-adashim, or you insist
that it be silent when you're cooking lentils, והמצווחת לגריסים, ve-ha-metzavachat le-grisim,
or you make, or you screech out, you make a lot of
noise when you're doing גריסים, grisim, which is I don't know what's
גריסים, grisim, some other type of thing, beans, some type of bean,
יש בו משום דרכי אמורי. yesh bo mishum Darkei Emori. That is
דרכי אמורי. Now that, you know, the גמרא Gemara said in another
place that when you grind spices and fragrances that the sound you
make at the time has a real impact on the quality. Here
it believes at least this list has it that it believes that
that was just superstition. המשתנת בפני קדרתה, Ha-mash-tenet bifnei kederatah, if a
woman urinates in front of her pot, בשביל שתתבשל מהרה, bishvil she-titbashel
mehera, to speed up the process, יש בו משום דרכי אמורי. yesh
bo mishum Darkei Emori. At least it's in front of. Okay. אבל
נותנין קיסם של תות,
Aval notnin kisam
shel
tut, but what you can do is you can put a twig
from תות tut which we say is strawberry, I think they say
mulberry or something, ושיברי זכוכית בקדרה, ve-shivrei zechuchit be-kedera, and a piece
of glass in the pot, בשביל שתתבשל מהרה. bishvil she-titbashel mehera. That
actually will work. That's not דרכי אמורי, that'll get it to cook
quicker. וחכמים אוסרים בשיברי זכוכית, Ve-chachamim osrin be-shivrei zechuchit, the Rabbis say
the pieces of glass. Maybe it's not דרכי אמורי, but it's סכנה,
sakana, you don't want a little glass. Actually, the obvious what you
do is, you know, for people who don't know, the obvious trick
is you try to get boiled water, you put some salt in
it, it lowers the boiling point of the water. Works better than
glass. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay, a rabbis taught: נותנים בול של
מלח לתוך הנר, nosnim bul shel melach l'toch haner, you can put
a clump of salt into a lamp, an oil lamp, בשביל שתאיר
ותדליק, bishvil she-ta'ir v'tadlik, that actually will make it burn clearer. Remember
yesterday we talked about mixing oil and salt and rubbing it on
your skin and somehow that's made it clear, the mixture. So that
actually works. ונותנים טיף של חרסית תחת הנר, v'nosnim tip shel charsisa
tachas haner, you can put plaster and like pottery under the under
the lamp, בשביל שתמתין ותדליק, bishvil she-tamtin v'tadlik, that actually somehow makes
it burn slower. Not clear how that works, but okay. You're not
actually putting it in the oil. אמר רב זוטרא: Amar Rav Zutra:
האי מאן דמיכסי שרגא דמשחא, hai man d'michasi sheraga d'mishcha, if you
cover an oil lamp, או מיגלי נפתא, o miglei nafta, or you
uncover a lamp that's burning with נפט, neft, a naphtha, which is
some type of kerosene, קעבר משום בל תשחית. ka-avar mishum Bal Taschis.
You transgress בל תשחית, Bal Taschis, not to wastefully destroy, because apparently
a covered oil lamp will burn faster and an uncovered kerosene lamp
will burn faster and it's just burning up, consuming the fuel faster
than is necessary, so you're over on בל תשחית. Bal Taschis. Now,
if you say חמרא וחיי לפום רבנן, chamra v'chayei l'fum rabbanan, wine
and life to the mouth of the rabbis, for the rabbis, it's
a toast, אין בו משום דרכי אמורי, ein bo mishum darkei emori,
but that's not דרכי אמורי. מעשה ברבי עקיבא שעשה משתה לבנו, Ma'aseh
b'Rabbi Akiva she-asah mishteh l'vno, Rabbi Akiva made a wedding feast for
his son, ועל כל כוס וכוס שהביא אמר, v'al kol kos v'kos
she-hevi amar, and every cup of wine that was brought
he said, חמרא וחיי לפום רבנן. chamra v'chayei l'fum rabbanan. Now, again,
presumably this was a very specific phrase. It was a common phrase
used. So any phrase that is sort of, you know, that is
sort of crystallized, you know, that is exactly those words, maybe there's
a concern that it's an incantation. Says, no, it's not an incantation,
it's just a standard toast.
חיי וחמרא לפום רבנן
ולפום תלמידיהם, chayei v'chamra
l'fum rabbanan
u'l'fum talmideihem, so he'd say wine
and life to the rabbis, wine and life to the rabbis and
to their students.
So that is the end.
Question: what about self-serving? That is true. I will say also that
there's an interesting discussion in the תוספתא Tosefta. about
whether you can say אסותא, asuta, whether you can say gesundheit. That
there's a word, it says gesundheit, once it says יש בו משום
דרכי אמורי, yesh bo mishum darkei emori, it's the custom of the
גרסא girsa there. Somehow, some have יש בו, yesh bo, some have
אין בו משום דרכי אמורי, ein bo mishum darkei emori, whether you're
allowed to say gesundheit or not. Okay. הדרן עלך במה אשה. Hadran
Alach Bameh Isha. ברוך שפטרני. Baruch She-petarani. What? Are you? Typically, in
the style of גמרא, Gemara you expect all these to be attributed
to someone. Yeah, this presumably is a lot of this is selection
from the תוספתא. Tosefta, But that's a good point, you know, that
it's just quoted, it's not saying it's from the תוספתא, it's just
this רשימתא, reshimta, these lists circulating, you know. Now, so we're going
to start the next פרק, perek, just read the משנה. Mishnah I
did want to just remind us also where we've gotten. We have
six פרקים prakim that have been about preparing for שבת. Shabbos. You
know, it started about way back, about telling us basic things about
carrying, but about like say having your vessels do a מלאכה melacha
before שבת Shabbos begins. Then it got into lighting candles, then it
got into putting food on the fire, insulating the food, what types
of things can you wear and not wear, presumably as you're getting
ready to, you know, put on your clothes for שבת. Shabbos. Can
you have your animals wear? And finally we get to the seventh
פרק perek and it's not by chance that there are six פרקים
prakim leading up to number seven, six days leading up to the
seventh, which is now where we actually start talking about the מלאכות
melachos per se. Obviously, that's been implicit a lot. It's also fascinating
to note how much has been about carrying, right? How much of
these six פרקים, prakim, two whole פרקים prakim devoted to animals and
people, their clothing which is about carrying. A whole major discussion in
the first פרק perek about carrying. Anyway, now we are finally getting
to the thing that talks about the מלאכות melachos themselves. Before we
get to the משנה Mishnah, a few דפים dappim from now that
lists the מלאכות, melachos, we're going to start with this משנה that
talks about the idea of different, if you transgress in different ways,
how many sin offerings you bring. Okay, so let's take a look
at this משנה, with this we will start at least. כלל גדול
אמרו בשבת. Klul gadol amru ba-Shabbos. They said a general principle by
שבת. Shabbos. כל השוכח עיקר שבת ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה. Kol
ha-shoche'ach ikar Shabbos v'asah melachos harbeh b'Shabbatos harbeh. If you forget the
idea of שבת, Shabbos, totally forgot that there is something called שבת,
Shabbos, and you do many types of מלאכה melacha on many types
of שבתות, Shabboses, אינו חייב אלא חטאת אחת. eino chayav ela chatas
achas. You bring one sin offering because you only made one mistake
essentially. You forgot the whole idea of שבת. Shabbos. So even though
you violated שבת Shabbos every single week and when you violated, you
violated multiple ways, there's only one mistake you made, one error, and
you bring one sin offering. היודע עיקר שבת. Ha-yode'a ikar Shabbos. Now
you know that there is שבת Shabbos in the world. But ועשה
מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה, v'asah melachos harbeh b'Shabbatos harbeh, but what you
forgot, it doesn't spell it out, is presumably you forgot what day
was שבת. Shabbos. So you kept on doing מלאכה melacha every שבת
Shabbos because maybe you thought שבת Shabbos was Friday, you got confused
or whatever. So you forgot not the concept of שבת, Shabbos, but
you forgot that that day was שבת. Shabbos. So every שבת Shabbos
you did many מלאכות, melachot, but חייב על כל שבת ושבת. chayav
al kol Shabbat veShabbat. You really, your mistake was that of forgetting
that the day was שבת. Shabbat. So you bring one sin-offering for
every שבת. Shabbat. If you were in this mistake, mistake for 20
weeks, you bring 20 sin-offerings, no matter how many different מלאכות melachot
you do, on every שבת Shabbos because your mistake was you forgot
that the day was שבת, Shabbat, and that you made 20 mistakes,
20 days you forgot that those were שבת, Shabbat, you bring 20
sin-offerings. Yes? If you're off by let's say a day in the
beginning, the subsequent ones are based on that original mistake. That is
true, and we're going to get to in the גמרא Gemara. that
the גמרא Gemara. says even though you have not, you have not
made an additional error, the fact that there's that there's חול chol
days between objectively defines them as different acts. So even though your
mistake was one, somehow it's defined as multiple for חטאת. chatat. We're
going to, it's going to be a major discussion in the גמרא
but it's an excellent point. Let's now talk about the third possibility.
היודע שהוא שבת ועשה מלאכות הרבה בשבתות הרבה. Hayodeia shehu Shabbat veasah
melachot harbe beShabbatot harbe. You know it's שבת, Shabbat, but the mistake
you made was you didn't know that this act was forbidden. That's
the most common mistake. You didn't realize you're not allowed to do
something on שבת. Shabbat. So you did it many different שבתות Shabbosot
over many different days. חייב על כל אב מלאכה ומלאכה. Chayav al
kol av melacha u'melacha. You're חייב chayav for every separate אב מלאכה
av melacha you do. So listen, that's important, because that means if
I was never told that you're not allowed to water your plants
on שבת, Shabbat, and every שבת Shabbos I water my plants and
I've been doing this for 20 שבתות, Shabboses, I only bring one
sin-offering because I made one mistake. I do not know that you're
allowed to water your plant. You're חייב על כל אב מלאכה ומלאכה
chayav al kol av melacha u'melacha for the number of אב מלאכה
av melacha that you have made an error about, not the number
of שבתות, Shabboses, but the number of אב מלאכה av melacha because
that's the mistake that you made. Okay? And the final point is
העושה מלאכות הרבה מעין מלאכה אחת. haoseh melachot harbe mei'ein melacha achat.
If you do many different different transgressions but they're all variations, they're
all part of one category, like I water my plants, I prune
my trees, I put manure in my plants, those are all subcategories
of planting, of encouraging growth. So I do all those things, אינו
חייב אלא חטאת אחת, eino chayav ela chatat achat, you only bring
one sin-offering because although it's multiple different things, it's all in the
same category. Okay? And therefore it is one sin-offering. So this will
be our focus for the next couple of days. All right. Thank
you so much. גמרא. גמרא. Here's the... שבת. Shabbat. I can't believe
it. תניא. Tanya. Here's the... שבת. Shabbat.